Ludvik Durchanek Collection
Ludvik Durchanek Collection
1951-1980
Durchanek, Ludvik
1.5 linear ft.
Original drawings and sketches, some correspondence, photographs of Durchanek's work, and exhibition catalogs.
149202
Biographical History
Czech sculptor and painter, born in 1902. For much of his life he lived and worked in New York. He died in 1976.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1902 to 1977, the Ludvik Durchanek Collection comprises Artwork, Correspondence/subject files, Writings, and Memorabilia of the Austrian-American artist.
Including some photographs of his paintings and sculpture, Artwork primarily consists of sketches done in secret while Durchanek was a staff member at the Hudson Valley State Hospital in the 1950s. The sketches were developed into a graphic narrative which was never published and is included in the collection.
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence/subject files contains communications with galleries and friends and the guest list and invitation from Durchanek's seventieth birthday party in 1972.
One untitled and unpublished autobiographical manuscript written in 1972 constitues Writings.
Memorabilia consists of clippings, printed material, and photographs of the artist and his work.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Sculptors; Durchanek, Ludvik, 1902-1976.; Hudson Valley State Hospital; Art, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Sketches.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ludvik Durchanek (1966) and Alice Boatwright (2004)
Inventory
- Artowork
  - Hospital sketchbook, 1951 (Box 1)
  - “The Institution” (working title “The hospital”), 1961; unpublished graphic narrative (Box 1)
  - Photographs of paintings and sculpture, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence / subject files
  - Barrett House, Poughkeepsie, NY “Ludvik Durchanek 1902-1976 Sculpture, Paintings and Drawings”, 1 Jul 1977 (Box 2)
  - Bennett, Alice and Peter, 1972-1976; undated (Box 2)
  - Boatwright, Alice, See Bennett, Alice and Peter
  - Bennett College Millbrook, NY - Durchanek Benefit, 28 Jan 1973 (Box 2)
  - Graham Gallery, New York, NY (Box 2)
  - His Excellency Leopold Gardens, Buchlovice, Moravia, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Seventieth Birthday Celebration, 29 Aug 1972 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Untitled and unpublished autobiography, 1972 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings
    - Fire at Durchanek's home in Wassaic, NY, Nov 1972 (Box 2)
    - “Red Scarf” fiction by Alice Boatwright, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1960 (Box 2)
  - Printed material
    - “The Great Society”, Feb 1966; Spotlight - Poughkeepsie, NY (Box 2)
    - “The Old man and the Seer”, Oct 1977; photo essay by Mary Ellen Andrews published in Camera 35 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Personal photographs (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous negatives (Box 2)
    - Rebuilding of Durchanek's home in Wassaic, NY (photo album), 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Miscellany
    - List of art work (Box 3)
    - Empty folder from hospital sketches (Box 3)